Hi am welcome, so in this video I'm
gonna show you about abstract and what
an abstract is in terms of coding.
So here we've got a program that creates a dog,
and if you've done the exercise that looks at
the different classes that we use, you would've
seen this in your documentation, now um, so what
we've got here is we've got the, uh, create dog
function that runs this program that sets the dog.
So, as you can see here, the dog is called Fred.
He's five years old.
He's his Jack Russell and down here we've
got all the methods that set this up.
The methods are listed not in the dog
class as you'd expect to find them, but
they're actually found in the pet class.
Now, the pet class has been set up as super class.
So a super class is a class that allows
other classes to inherit from it.
At the moment, the dog class inherits from
the super class, and the only variable that's
passed through the dog class is the breed.
The dog inherits the name and the age classes.
The dog inherits the name and the
age variables from the pet class.
Okay, So at the moment in my
program, I've created a dog, cla a.
At the moment in this program, I have created
a dog object, but I can also do the same with
a pet object, so I could create a pet object.
So PET P one equals new pet.
I could then set it up, so it's asking for a name.
So I've got no name and it's asking for
an age, and I've got no age like so.
That's great if you wanna be able
to create an object from pet.
But don't forget, pet is a super class and most
of the objects, for example, I could create a cat
class, I could create a fish class, and so forth.
Most of those objects would
have a specific class type.
So I would need to create a class
type, so if the pet shop decided to
bring in reptiles, I would then have to
bring in a reptile class and so forth.
Okay, because they all inherit from the pet class,
but I don't want the system to set up a pet.
So what I would do is I would go into the
pet class and set it as an abstract class.
Now, an abstract class basically means that the,
the abstract class basically means that once I've
actually set it, I can't create an object from it.
So if we go back to our Create Dog class, you'll
see now that it's gonna say Pet is abstract,
cannot be instantiated, so we can't create a pet.
Okay, so we can't create a pet
object, so I have to get rid of that.
So this will force me now to make sure
that I create subclasses of the pet.
You'll see that the dog still works fine, and
as I said, I could create a cat class and it
would adopt the attributes from the pet class.
So that's what an abstract class
will do, you basically create the
abstract class, but you need to create
subclasses to, to use the benefits of it.
Okay?
There's another thing that's also, uh,
you can also set up in the pet class.
So if I go into the pet class, a moment, I can
also set up what's called an abstract method.
Okay, so we've got some methods down
here, and they all work pretty well.
Well, let's create, uh, an
abstract method of sleep.
So as it's at the moment set, it's public void
sleep, so let's make it an abstract method.
Now, the syntax for the abstract method
is different to that of a normal method.
I don't need anything in these curly braces,
so I'll get rid of them, just like that and
you'll be asking yourself, well, that's all
well and good, but that sleep method doesn't
do anything and that's absolutely correct.
In terms of the pet class, the
abstract method doesn't do anything.
However, if I go over to my dog class,
I've got a squiggly line under here, and
what the dog class is now saying is that
I must either declare an abstract or
implement an abstract method called sleep.
So what it's saying is, for me to complete
this method, I need to create a sleep method.
So I'm gonna create a sleep method now.
So let's do that public void sleep.
Um, I'm not gonna pass anything into
it, and I'm just gonna simply do, uh, an
output, which is gonna go all the z's.
Okay, now, because I've created this sleep
method, I'm up to the top, the little squiggly
line has gone, so it's now happy with that
because the sleep method has been put in place.
So, that shows you how to do an abstract
class and how to do an abstract method.
So just to recap, an abstract class is a class
that you cannot instantiate you can't create
an object from it, but all the subclasses,
as long as you don't make the subclasses
abstract classes, they can be created and
that's why you would do it and think of it
like making a massive blueprint of all the
objects that inherits from the the PET class.
And then there's the abstract method and what
the abstract method does is it makes sure
that I create a method in each of the subclass
of that super class of that abstract class.
Okay.
I'm calling it a super class because it is
like the parent class and all the classes
that inherit from it are all child classes.
Okay?
So I hope you enjoyed that.
Uh, in my next video I'm gonna
talk a little bit about interface.